Good morning. Today's דף daf is ל"ח, Lamed Chet, 35. We pick
up at the משנה Mishna at the bottom of ל"ג עמוד ב'.
Lamed Gimmel Amud Bet. We had just had the whole discussion about
how many הדסים, hadasim, how many ערבות. aravot.
It's worth mentioning two things I should say before we continue, which
is number one, that there was a practice
at the time of the ראשונים Rishonim and even until today of
taking many more than the minimum number of הדסים, hadasim, sometimes also
of ערבות. aravot. And the question is, how is that allowed? I
mean, normally we say that if you do more than something,
it's a problem of בל תוסיף. bal tosif. So if you look
very briefly at the תוספות, Tosfot, תוספות Tosfot says ארבע נחל שתים.
Arba Nachal Shtayim. תוספות Tosfot says אפילו נותן כמה הדסים וכמה ערבות
בלולב אין זה בל תוסיף, afilu noten kama hadasim ve-kama aravot be-lulav
ein zeh bal tosif, even if you have many, many הדסים hadasim
and ערבות, aravot, it's not בל תוסיף. bal tosif. אפילו מאן דאמר
צריך אגד אלא אם כן מוסיף מין אחר, afilu madem tzarich eged
ella im ken mosif min acher, only if you put in something
extraneous. And this clearly was reflecting a widespread practice
and
trying to explain why it was not a violation. One way certainly
of understanding it
is that the number of three הדסים hadasim and two ערבות aravot
are a minimum, not a maximum. And part of that could be
understood because if the idea is like the primary thing is the
לולב lulav and the אתרוג etrog and those are singular and the
הדסים hadasim and the ערבות aravot are the ones things that are
in the multiple, it seemed more of like as a bunch of
הדסים hadasim and a bunch of ערבות aravot which two being just
the minimum amount in the bunch. But still, if you conceptualize it
more as a bunch, then the number is more of a minimum
number and therefore you can have even more, which might also explain
why רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael allows two to be cut off and
one not to be cut off. Again, if you think of it
more less as individual units and more of a bunch, something like
that makes a little bit more sense.
Okay, I guess we'll end with that. Let's go on now and
go to the next משנה. Mishna.
Let's take a look.
Right, okay, so the משנה Mishna says the following. אתרוג הגזול והיבש,
etrog ha-gazul ve-ha-yavesh, if you have a stolen or dried up אתרוג,
etrog, פסול, pasul, it's invalid. של אשרה ושל עיר הנדחת, shel ashera
ve-shel ir ha-nidachat, if it's of a אשרה ashera worshiped tree or
an עיר הנדחת, ir ha-nidachat, a city that is condemned, פסול, pasul,
it's invalid. So so far it's just like the beginning of all
the other משניות. mishnayot.
של ערלה, shel orlah, פסול. pasul. Now here we get to something
that's unique to אתרוג. etrog. If it's ערלה, orlah, if it's within
the first three years, then it's going to be invalid. We'll see,
but obviously it cannot be eaten then, and we're going to see
in the גמרא Gemara that an אתרוג etrog has to be able
to be eaten in order to have the possibility of being eaten
in order to be כשר. kosher. We'll see why in the גמרא.
Gemara. של תרומה טמאה, shel trumah tmei'ah, פסול. pasul. If it's תרומה
טמאה, trumah tmei'ah, which also cannot be eaten, then it's invalid. של
תרומה טהורה, shel trumah tehorah, if it's טהור tahor תרומה, trumah, which
can be eaten at least by כהנים, Kohanim, לא יטול, lo yitol,
don't take, ואם נטל כשר, ve-im natal kasher, and if you took
it, it would be כשר. kosher. So we'll see why לכתחילה lechatchila
you shouldn't take it. של דמאי, shel demai, how about דמאי, demai,
which is taken from the עמי הארץ, amei ha-aretz, which biblically you
could assume is okay but rabbinically they required you to take מעשר
ma'aser and תרומת מעשר. trumat ma'aser. The one thing you did have
to take was תרומה, trumah, that you could assume that the עמי
הארץ amei ha-aretz took. So what's the story there? There it's not
edible until you do the taking of
תרומות ומעשרות, trumot ve-ma'asrot, but that's only rabbinic. So there בית שמאי
פוסלין ובית הלל מכשירין. Beit Shammai poslin ve-Beit Hillel machshirin. בית שמאי
Beit Shammai says it's invalid and בית הלל Beit Hillel says it's
כשר. kosher. Presumably it's obvious that טבל tevel would not be valid
because it could not be eaten, at least not in that state.
Okay, של מעשר שני בירושלים. shel ma'aser sheni bi-Yerushalayim. Let's say you
have something that could be eaten but it's not really totally being
able to eat at your discretion. It's מעשר שני, ma'aser sheni, which
has to be eaten in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, and you are in ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, so it is able to be eaten. So what's the story?
לא יטול, lo yitol, similar הלכה, halacha, don't take it. We'll see
why. ואם נטל כשר, ve-im natal kasher, but if you did take
it, it's okay because again, it's able to be eaten. So once
again we see this idea of that it has to be able
to have the potential of being eaten. Yeah, Charlie?
Fourth year ערלה? orlah?
Fourth year ערלה, orlah, you mean נטע רבעי. neta revai. Yeah, that's
a good point why it's not mentioned, especially since we're talking about
fruit.
And מעשר שני ma'aser sheni which has a similar...
Right, so presumably it would be the same. It's a good point.
Okay, עלתה חזזית על רובו, altzehaziz al rubo, a fair are like
warts on the majority of the אתרוג, etrog, or נטל פטמתו, natal
pitamto, if the פטם pitam is removed, which is like the little
sort of, you know, we all know what the פטם pitam is.
It's that the, it's the little stick in the bulb at the
top, like the little mushroom cloud at the top. So then, or
נקלף niklaf if it's been peeled, נסדק nisdak cracked, ניקב וחסר כל
שהוא, nikav ve-chasar kol shehu, if it has a hole and a
little bit is missing as a result of the
hole, that's one...
הוא שחזזיתו מיעוטו hu shechazazito miyuto if however there's a wart on
the minority of it, נטל עוקצו natal uktzo if the stem has
been removed, not the פטם. pitam.
ניקב ולא חסר כל שהוא nikav velo chasar kol shehu or it
has a hole but nothing is missing as a result of the
hole, you like put a pin in it and nothing actually came
away,
in that case כשר kasher it is kosher. So that's like the
flip side of the first list. So we moved from these, the
first the general list then to the issues about being able to
eat it
and then to these aesthetic points. Now,
אתרוג הכושי פסול. etrog hakushi pasul. If an אתרוג etrog is black,
it is invalid. והירוק ככרתי vehayarok kekarti if it's as green as
a leek, רבי מאיר מכשיר רבי יהודה פוסל. Rabbi Meir machshir Rabbi
Yehuda posel. Rabbi Meir says it's kosher, Rabbi Yehuda says it's invalid.
Some of this was quoted in an earlier גמרא. Gemara. שיעור אתרוג
הקטן, shiur etrog hakatan, the size of the smallest אתרוג, etrog, רבי
מאיר אומר כאגוז רבי יהודה אומר כביצה. Rabbi Meir omer ke'egoz Rabbi
Yehuda omer kebeitza. The size of a nut or the size of
an egg. ובגדול, uvigadol, how big is the maximum size? כדי שיאחוז
שנים בידו דברי רבי יהודה. kedai sheyochaz shenayim beyado divrei Rabbi Yehuda.
Rabbi Yehuda says it has to, it can't be so big that
you can't hold two in one hand. You have to be able
to hold two in a hand. רבי
יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yose omer, Rabbi Yose says, אפילו אחד בשתי ידיו,
afilu echad bishtei yadav, it could be huge even if it takes
two hands to hold one. So we saw in an earlier גמרא
Gemara that these debates at the end about the color and the
size are not necessarily debates about aesthetics, about הדר. hadar. They could
be debates about whether it's considered גמר פירא, gmar peira, פרי, peri,
is it considered like the fruit is ripe and full and complete?
And the issue about the size, that it can't be too big,
might be just an issue about a concern of dropping it. So
it's possible to read all of these as aesthetics, possible to read
them as other types of concerns. Okay, now we pick up with
the גמרא Gemara at the top of ל"ה
עמוד ב'. lamed hei amud bet.
Okay,
right. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: תנו רבנן,
tanu rabbanan, our Rabbis taught. פרי
עץ הדר, pri etz hadar, a fruit of a beautiful tree, שטעם
עצו ופריו שוה. shetaam etzo upiryo shaveh. So again we're reading the
פרי pri and the עץ, etz, the juxtaposition of the two, it
has to be like, it's almost like you know that מדרש midrash
on מעשה בראשית maaseh bereishit where God says תוצא הארץ, totze ha'aretz,
what is it? עץ פרי עשה פרי. etz pri oseh pri. So
עץ פרי, etz pri, the fruit, the wood of
the tree itself has to be fruit, has to taste like fruit.
And then of course the land didn't listen and it just took,
and it had it that the fruit was, had the taste but
not the tree. So here too, פרי עץ, pri etz, literally the
fruit of a tree, but it's also reading like an עץ פרי,
etz pri, like the tree itself has to taste like the fruit.
עץ שטעם עצו ופריו שוה, etz shetaam etzo upiryo shaveh, an עץ
etz that a tree that even the wood has something of the
taste of the fruit. הוי אומר זה אתרוג, hevei omer zeh etrog,
that's an אתרוג. etrog. Now I don't know, I've never tried it,
but okay, I don't think it means necessarily that it's
digestible, I never chewed the bark, how about you? Or the twig.
I don't assume it means it's digestible, but anyway it has something
of that taste. ואימא פלפלין, ve'eima pilpelin, maybe pepper?
Okay, apparently pepper, the bark, the vine, actually I looked this up,
so pepper is a, is a perennial vine, it's like a woody
vine, okay, where we get our peppercorn from. So apparently the vine
itself has some type of a peppery taste. כדתניא, kidtanya, and how
do I know that? Because we taught in the ברייתא. baraita. היה
רבי מאיר אומר ממשמע שנאמר, hayah Rabbi Meir omer mimashma shene'emar, since
the verse says now by
ערלה, orlah, ונטעתם כל עץ, unetatem kol etz, you shall plant any
tree. איני יודע שהוא עץ מאכל? aini yodea shehu etz maachal? Obviously
it's a, it's a tree that provides food because then it speaks
about the fruit of the tree. This is a verse about ערלה,
orlah, so the later thing speaks about וערלתם ערלתו את פריו, ve'araltem
orlato et piryo, you can't eat the fruit. So why does it
have to describe it as an עץ מאכל, etz maachal, a food
tree? מה תלמוד לומר עץ מאכל, mah talmud lomar etz maachal, why
does the Torah go out of its way to call it a
food tree? מה
תלמוד לומר עץ מאכל, mah talmud lomar etz maachal, where am I?
עץ שטעם עצו ופריו שוה, etz shetaam etzo upiryo shaveh, to tell
me that even the food, the tree is something of a food,
that the tree itself tastes like the fruit. Okay, and what is
that? הוי אומר, hevei omer, so which tree is this that the
bark itself has some of the taste of the fruit? זה פלפלין,
zeh pilpelin, that's a pepper vine.
ללמדך שהציץ של פלפלין חייבין בערלה, lelamedcha shehitzitz shel pilpelin chayavin be'orlah,
and the reason that the Torah goes out of its way to
talk about a pepper vine here or to hint to a pepper
vine is to teach you that even peppers are obligated in ערלה,
orlah, that you should not think that they're not fruit, right? They
grow from a vine, maybe they wouldn't be considered fruit, it is
a vine that lasts for at least three years.
So number one to teach you they're fruit. Number two as תוספות
Tosafot says, since most people don't eat peppers, we're talking about peppercorn
not what we call bell peppers, since most people don't eat peppers
straight, you might say they're not, don't constitute a fruit even though
they're a spice. But apparently they are edible before they get, you
know, while they're still moist, before they get hardened. So anyway, so
the Torah is telling you that this thing is a tree, it
is fruit, and it is חייב בערלה. chayav be'orlah.
ואין ארץ ישראל חסרה כלום. ve'ein eretz yisrael chasera klum. And the
other thing it's telling you is that the land of Israel isn't
lacking of anything, it even has peppercorns, שנאמר, shene'emar, as the verse
says, לא תחסר כל בו, lo techsar kol bo, you won't lack
anything in the land of Israel. So even peppercorns.
Okay, so anyway, what do you see? You see from that מדרש
הלכה midrash halacha that it understands that peppers are taste like the
fruit, that the tree tastes like the fruit. So maybe that's what
an אתרוג etrog is. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, משום דלא
אפשר, mishum d'lo efshar, it couldn't be that that's what the תורה
Torah wants us to do, that's impossible. Why is that impossible? היכי
נעביד, Heichi naavid, what do you want us to do? ננקוט חדא,
Ninkot chada, take one peppercorn, לא מיתחזי לקיחתו, lo mitchazei lekichato, that
would not be obvious that you're taking anything. When it says, you
know, it says ולקחתם לכם, ulakachtem lachem, presumably it has to be
somewhat visible or evident what you're doing. ננקוט תרי או תלת, Ninkot
tray o tlat, take two or three, I guess, I don't know
if two or three peppercorns is any more obvious than one, but
okay, maybe at least it's more obvious to you that you're doing
anything. אמר רחמנא Amar rachmana פרי עץ הדר pri etz hadar אמר
רחמנא, amar rachmana, it says one fruit, ולא שנים ושלשה פירות, velo
shnayim v'shlosha peirot, not two or three. הלכך לא אפשר. Hilkach lo
efshar. Therefore it can't be. So this is again this idea as
we've seen by almost all of the ארבע מינים arba minim that
the תורה, Torah, thank you, except for ערבות נחל aravot nachal where
it was a little bit more explicit, where the גמרא Gemara tries
to show how we can derive from these more descriptive words how
we can derive exactly what we identify as the species of the
לולב. lulav. And again I'll repeat to you what the רמב"ם Rambam
says, where the רמב"ם Rambam says it's all, it's hard to imagine
that we really didn't know and somehow it was just these דרשות
drashot that led us onto the right fruit. Because as you see
in the גמרא, Gemara, it's vague enough, there's other possibilities. And the
רמב"ם Rambam says we always knew by tradition what these were and
the גמרא Gemara is just sort of retrofitting it. That's the רמב"ם's
Rambam's read of this גמרא, Gemara, and it does deal with a
problem about how did you really get from this verse to something
that is exactly this, given that there should have been, could have
theoretically been a lot of other possibilities. But one minute, but right
now the one דרשה drasha we have said is that it tastes
like the tree, the tree tastes like the fruit, and that is
the אתרוג. etrog. Yes.
You know, we distinguish between fruit and vegetable by the way, depends
upon the function of the item on the plant. Right, תוספות Tosafot
here at the very top says, לעתיד לבוא ירק ובושמיה עץ שפל.
l'atid lavo yerak u'vishmeish eitz shafel. Do they have like a whole
different concept to develop the structure of the?
Yes, I did want to get into that. That is true, meaning
what is the halakhic different distinct categorization of fruits and vegetables? I
mean you are right that like there's first of all just for
us there's a difference between botanically and sort of
vernacularly. Botanically it has to do with the fact that there are
are the seeds contained you know within it or something, which means
that like a cucumber and a tomato is a fruit. And
but in the vernacular I think we tend to identify the sweet
things as fruits more and the more and the more blander things
as vegetables or I don't know some type of distinction like that.
Halakhically, yeah, there's questions about ערלה, orlah, there's questions about ברכות, brachot,
בורא פרי העץ, borei pri ha'eitz, בורא פרי האדמה. borei pri ha'adamah.
One classic definition is whether the bark, the trunk from which it
grows lasts from year to year or not. So that's one major
distinguishing category. So yes, but so that is an important question in
areas of הלכה halakhah what exactly are the distinct ways of categorizing.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, so that's one
definition which is it tastes, the tree tastes like the fruit.
רבי אומר, Rebbi omer, רבי Rebbi says, אל תקרי הדר, al tikrei
hadar, don't read it beautiful, אלא הדיר, ela ha-dir, like the pen,
like a pen for sheep. מה דיר זה, Ma dir zeh, the
same way a pen of sheep, יש בו גדולים וקטנים, yesh bo
gedolim u'ktanim, you have older sheep and newborn sheep, תמימים ובעלי מומים,
tmimim u'ba'alei mumim, ones perfect and ones very blemished. הכא נמי יש
בו גדולים וקטנים תמימים ובעלי מומים. Hacha nami yesh bo gedolim u'ktanim
tmimim u'ba'alei mumim. You take a look at an אתרוג etrog and
you've got big ones and small ones and perfect ones and blemished
ones, right? Because you have really very bizarre shaped אתרוגים etrogim and
very different types of shaped אתרוגים. etrogim. So the גמרא Gemara says
one minute, אטו שאר פירות לית בהו גדולים וקטנים תמימים ובעלי מומים?
atu shear peirot leis bo gedolim u'ktanim tmimim u'ba'alei mumim? You tell
me other fruit you don't go look at a tree, you don't
have big, you know, you don't have ones that are more developed,
ones that are smaller developed, ones that are more perfect, ones that
are less perfect. So the גמרא Gemara says fine, אלא הכי קאמר,
ela hachi kama, this was the point of the דרשה. drasha. עד
שבאים קטנים עדיין גדולים קיימים. Ad sheba'im ktanim adayin gedolim kayamim. It
doesn't just mean that you have big and small ones from the
same year. It means that while there's still the older ones from
last year, new ones are already now blossoming. So that by an
אתרוג etrog you have the tree can last on the, the fruit
can last on the tree for multiple
years. And that's the idea of דיר. dir. Okay, so now we're
going to have a דרשה drasha that maybe says the same point
a little bit more
straightforwardly. רבי אבהו אמר, Rebbi Abbahu amar, אל תקרי הדר, al tikrei
hadar, don't read beautiful, אלא הדר, ela hadar, which dwells. דבר שדר
באילנו משנה לשנה, Davar she-dar b'ilano mishana l'shana, something that dwells on
the tree from year to year, which is similarly to the point
of. רבי Rebbi except using a different understanding of the word דר
dar to dwell as opposed to a דיר dir like a pen
of animal. It is worth pointing out about רבי Rebbi some of
the interesting associations talking about this like, you know, this like pen
of sheep because this is now the second time that we've had
an association of לולב lulav with קרבנות. korbanot. The opening of the
סוגיא sugiah was, right, the והבאתם גזול ואת הפיסח, ve-heveitem gazul ve-et
ha-piseach,
we learned the idea of מצוה הבאה בעבירה mitzvah ba'ah b'aveira from
פסוקים pesukim about bringing קרבנות korbanot and not bringing
a stolen קרבן. korban. And here the idea of talking about a
pen of sheep, right? And what do you do with sheep religiously?
You bring it as a קרבן. korban. And if that wasn't obvious,
then it says תמימים ובעלי מומים, temimim u'va'alei mumim, right, which is
a phrase that's only used by a קרבן, korban, right, unblemished and
blemished. So that's quite an interesting idea about the association here with
the ארבע מינים arba minim with קרבנות. korbanot. And particularly by the
אתרוג, etrog, I would say it's probably the one thing in our
religious life which we sort of treat like we would do the
whole inspection of blemishes that they used to do in the בית
המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, right? I mean we try a little bit with
the לולב lulav and a little bit with the הדס, hadass, but
really with the אתרוג, etrog, if you certainly some people with the
magnifying glass and looking for those tiny spots. So it's interesting to
think about how that becomes then a type of a, you know,
pseudo-קרבן. korban. What exactly is the association in terms of סוכות Sukkot
with that? I mean to the degree that you associate the סוכות
Sukkot with the building of the משכן, Mishkan, which some do because
the timing sort of works out, and again issues we spoken about
before about ענני כבוד ananei kavod and like you know the sense
of God's presence in the סוכה. sukkah. So that whole period, you
know, has that more מקדש mikdash could have that more מקדש mikdash
association. Also right at the heels of יום כיפור Yom Kippur which
is obviously going לפני ולפנים lifnai ve-lifnim in the בית המקדש. Beit
Hamikdash. Anyway it is interesting thinking about that implicit association in רבי'ס
Rebbi's statement. A huge number of
קרבנות. korbanot. Well that's also true, I didn't think about that, you're
right, seventy the seventy oxen and right, that's a very good point.
This disagreement between רבי Rebbi and
רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu
is another case where they both know what the answer is going
to be. Right, yeah no that's not how we get that answer.
We don't read דיר, dir, we read דר, dar, right?
You're
saying the same thing, exactly, we're all working towards the same answer.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: בן עזאי אומר, Ben
Azzai omer, אל תקרי הדר, al tikrei hadar, don't read הדר hadar
אלא הדור ela hadur or אידור, idur, שכן בלשון יווני קורין למים
אידור. sheken bilshon Yavani korin le-mayim idur. In Greek, now we're using
Greek to explain the word, the word for water is אידור, idur,
so and therefore an אתרוג etrog is described as a water tree.
ואיזה זה שגדל על כל מים? ve-eizeh zeh she-gadel al kol mayim?
And what
and what type of a tree is one that grows can grow
on all types of water meaning irrigated and rainwater and so on?
הוי אומר זה אתרוג. hevei omer zeh etrog. It's an אתרוג, etrog,
which is interesting because you know I assume an אתרוג etrog is
more of like a Mediterranean tropical type of a plant, which I
assume means it needs a lot of water. גדלים על כל מים
gadelim al kol mayim usually doesn't mean that it needs a lot
of water, usually means that it can manage in a lot of
different water situations. But maybe it does mean I don't know maybe
for this it means that it needs a lot of water. By
the way I looked it up the word for Greek is the
Greek word for water was found not at least modern Greek sounded
nothing like אידור. idur. I don't know about classical Greek but it
sounded something like I don't know.
Steinsaltz says it's related to hydor.
Hydor? What do you mean?
As in hydraulic. Oh hydraulic, hydro.
See the
H in modern Greek often is not spelled out.
Oh, so hydro. Because the word for water in ancient in in
in contemporary
Greek is nero or nero or something, but that's a good point,
hydro.
Modern Greek words are often completely different from classical Greek.
Oh that's a good point, I don't think about that, you're right,
hydro, that works out beautifully. I will say again what רמב"ן על
התורה Ramban al ha-Torah says, רמב"ן על התורה Ramban al ha-Torah makes
a very nice point, he says the word אתרוג, etrog, he says
he points out that the Aramaic word for beautiful is מרגג, mirageg,
and therefore אתרוג etrog he said the word he speculates maybe maybe
is an Aramaic word and really means beautiful, and that actually creates
הדר hadar rather than being descriptive could be actually seen as that
is the name, the name of it is אתרוג etrog the name
is beautiful. You know, as I pointed out like we have fruit
called passion fruit, you know, or how about an orange? An orange
is not just the color, it's the name of the fruit. So
he actually says הדר hadar beautiful and אתרוג etrog might be essentially
the same word. So that's the way the רמב"ן Ramban tries to
suggest that that's why the word הדר hadar means an אתרוג. etrog.
Okay so now we've that we've identified it we continue. Asher ve-she...
asher ve-she... אשרה ושל עיר הנדחת פסול. ve-shel ashera ve-shel ir ha-nidachat
pasul.
So now we're going to have we haven't been analyzing this in
the הדס hadass and the ערבה aravah because we did it by
the לולב, lulav, but clearly now the גמרא Gemara is going to
spend more time on the אתרוג etrog so we're sort of recapping
some of the stuff that we did earlier. So why אשרה ashera
ועיר הנדחת ve-ir ha-nidachat is פסול? pasul? מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? כיון
דלשרפה קאי, keivan de-lisreifa qai,
since you have to burn it, כתויי מכתת שיעוריה, kitutei mechitatch shiurei,
it's like it's already burnt up like there's no שיעור, shiur, the
fact that it has to be destroyed undermines its significance and therefore
it cannot be considered it's no longer can't be used for a
מצוה. mitzvah. We did skip over גזול. gazul. and again revisit this
question of whether it was an issue of ownership on the first
day or was it a מצווה הבאה בעבירה mitzvah haba'ah b'aveira on
the other days. Now we look to the unique aspects of אתרוג
esrog and all of these all of these
requirements that it be able to be fit for being eaten. So
ערלה orlah פסול, pasul, if it's from ערלה orlah it's invalid, the
first three years. מאי טעמא Mai ta'ama what's the reason? פליגי בה
Pligi ba רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiya bar Abba ורבי אמי.
v'Rabbi Ami.
So a debate of רבי חייא בר אבא Rabbi Chiya bar Abba
and רבי אמי. Rabbi Ami. חד אמר Chad amar לפי שאין בה
היתר אכילה. lefi she'ein ba heter achila. One says because it's not
able to be eaten, halachically it is not permissible to be eaten.
וחד אמר, V'chad amar, the other one says, לפי שאין בה דין
ממון. lefi she'ein ba din mamon. Because if there's no monetary value
to it because it is אסור בהנאה. asur b'hana'ah. ערלה Orlah you're
not allowed to derive benefit, so anything that you're not allowed to
derive benefit is considered to be worthless. There is an interesting discussion
in the ראשונים rishonim since biblically you could derive benefit in an
unnatural way, in an unusual way, why is it saying that it
really has no value? But the basic answer is that doesn't it
matter, even if you could find a technical way to derive some
benefit, since you're not supposed to derive any benefit halachically, it is
considered to have to be worthless. So for example, it's the classic
case of a man who marries a woman with something that is
ערלה. orlah. So she's not married because it's not considered to have
a שוה פרוטה, shaveh prutah, it doesn't even have a penny's worth
of value to it. So that's the reason. The reason is and
the way רש"י Rashi explains it, it ultimately goes back to the
idea of לכם, lachem, yours, so therefore it can't be considered yours
if it is something that you have no right to derive benefit
from and it has no value. So one emphasizes the issue of
is there any monetary value to it, the other is whether you're
allowed to eat it. Now why should you have to have a
requirement to be able to eat it? So רש"י Rashi and then
תוספות Tosfos following רש"י Rashi's lead, both say that it's part of
the same idea of לכם. lachem. It can't be considered yours if
you can't have this type of basic benefit. Something that's a fruit,
if you're not able to eat it then to what degree can
you really call it yours? And therefore it's a really לכם lachem
requirement. So according to רש"י, Rashi, it's two variations of how you
explain the idea of לכם. lachem. לכם Lachem being able to get
practical benefit, eat it, or לכם lachem in a sort of, you
know, much more accounting sense that it actually has some value. That's
the way רש"י Rashi says it, two variations of לכם. lachem. According
to that, it probably would only be invalid on the first day.
The other days you don't need לכם, lachem, it would be fine.
רמב"ם Rambam in פירוש המשניות Peirush Hamishnayos has a much more creative
explanation of why you need היתר אכילה. heter achila. So monetary value
that's based on לכם. lachem. But היתר אכילה heter achila רמב"ם Rambam
says is because it can't be called a fruit, right? The Torah
says פרי עץ הדר. pri eitz hadar. How could you call something
a fruit if you can't eat it? Okay, so I mean, I
guess you could, you could talk about poisonous berries, but the Torah
wouldn't call it a fruit if it wasn't able to even if
what's preventing it from being eaten is physically it could be eaten,
but הלכה halacha that's preventing it from being eaten, that would undermine
its identity as fruit. So according to that, if you can't eat
it, it would be a problem for all seven days, it's not
just a definition of ownership. Okay, and that's what the רמב"ם Rambam
says is the issue here of היתר אכילה. heter achila. So let's
take a look. קסלקא דעתך, Kasalka deitach, so we are assuming, says
the גמרא, Gemara, מאן דבעי היתר אכילה, man d'ba'ei heter achila,
the one that demands it be fit to be eaten, לא בעי
דין ממון, lo ba'ei din mamon, would not require that you actually
that it actually have a monetary value. You'd have to own it
but it wouldn't need a monetary value. ומאן דבעי דין ממון, Uman
d'ba'ei din mamon, and if you demand the monetary value, לא בעי
היתר אכילה, lo ba'ei heter achila, you would not necessarily need to
be able to eat it. Now what are scenarios that you could
have one without the other? So רש"י Rashi gives you the scenario.
First of all, what we're going to get to in the גמרא
Gemara is מעשר שני. maaser sheini. מעשר שני Maaser sheini in ירושלים
Yerushalayim you're allowed to eat. There's a מצווה mitzvah to eat. But
there's a position of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that it's not yours,
you're basically it's G-d's. Like when כהנים kohanim eat a קרבן, korban,
there's a מצווה mitzvah to eat it but it's not their קרבן.
korban. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says the same is true about
מעשר שני maaser sheini in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. It's not really yours, but
you have a מצווה mitzvah to eat it. So that would be
something you could eat that does not have a דין ממון, din
mamon, does not have any monetary value. What type of a thing
would have monetary value that you're not allowed to eat? So רש"י
Rashi I think says טבל tevel is the example, because you would
I think I'm pretty sure רש"י Rashi says, yes, טבל. tevel. Says
טבל tevel has monetary value because once you take תרומות ומעשרות, terumos
u'maasros, you'll be able to eat it. So nobody's giving away טבל,
tevel, it's not worthless. Okay,
therefore טבל tevel is something that has what? All kinds of מאכלות
אסורות.
maachalos
asuros.
Right, that's true, but you have to have one that works with
an אתרוג. esrog.
But right, it would have to something that would be אסור asur
to be eaten but wouldn't be אסור בהנאה asur b'hana'ah would also
be a related point. And that's a good thing, that's a good
point. As long as there's no איסור הנאה issur hana'ah it has
a monetary value. And even more so טבל tevel which you'll be
able to eat eventually, but right now you're not able to eat
it. So we're assuming, says the גמרא, Gemara, that these are mutually
exclusive categories or that they're debating both points. One position only wants
you to be able to eat it, does not care that it
have any value, and the other position wants it to have value,
it does not care whether or not you're able to eat it.
So now the גמרא Gemara is going to test that theory. Let's
take a look. תנן, Tnan, we taught in
our
Mishnah. תנן, Tnan, how can מעשר שני maaser sheini have no value
but can't you
bring
the money, what, can't you bring the money. Yes, but מעשר שני
ma'aser sheni in ירושלים Yerushalayim can
be eaten by you, it's a מצווה mitzvah to be eaten, but
it's not considered to be yours. So you're right, there דין ממון
din mamon does not so much mean that it doesn't have value,
it more means that in no way are you considered to be
the monetary the owner of it. Okay. Okay. All right. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this: בשלמא למאן דאמר לפי שאין בו היתר
אכילה, bishlama l'man d'amar lefi she'ein bo heter akhila, so תנן, tnan,
our משנה mishna teaches, שבתרומה טמאה, she'bitruma tmeiah, that if it's תרומה
טמאה, truma tmeiah, you're not יוצא, yotze, because תרומה טמאה truma tmeiah
you're not allowed to eat. So בשלמא bishlama it's got to be
burnt, so פסול. pasul. בשלמא למאן דאמר לפי שאין בו היתר אכילה,
bishlama l'man d'amar lefi she'ein bo heter akhila, if there's a requirement
that you be able to eat it, שפיר, shapir, now we understand
why you're not
יוצא yotze with תרומה טמאה.
truma tmeiah. הרי אלו, harey elu, למאן דאמר לפי שאין בו דין
ממון, l'man d'amar lefi she'ein bo din mamon, if the issue is
not that you have to eat it but it has to have
some value and you have to be considered the monetary owner, so
אמאי, amai, why is תרומה טמאה truma tmeiah not good? הרי מסיקה
תחת תבשילו, harey masika tachat tavshilo, what do you do with תרומה
טמאה? truma tmeiah? You can use it to burn to make firewood.
So if you can make firewood out of your אתרוג, esrog, you
are the owner, it does have value, it has permitted use, so
why should it not be good if you don't if all you
need is this idea of monetary ownership? So the גמרא Gemara says
אלא, ella, you're right, בהיתר אכילה כולי עלמא לא פליגי דבעינא. b'heter
akhila kuli alma lo pligi d'ba'ina. You're right, everybody agrees it needs
to be able to be eaten. And all the cases in our
משנה, mishna, the problem was was that it couldn't be eaten. That's
exactly the issue. You're right. And again, according to the רמב"ם, Rambam,
according to רש"י, Rashi, there's an aspect of ownership by a fruit,
by an אתרוג, esrog, that is necessary. It would you wouldn't be
considered the owner if you couldn't eat it. And according to רמב"ם,
Rambam, it's basic definition of being able to call the אתרוג esrog
a fruit. So everybody agrees you have to be able to eat
it. And that's why the cases in our משנה mishna are excluded.
כי פליגי, ki pligi, what's the debate? בדין ממון, b'din mamon, whether
even if you are able to eat it, does it also have
to be considered to be your money, your property? מר סבר היתר
אכילה בעינן, mar savar heter akhila ba'inan, one person holds all you
need is to be able to be eaten, to eat it. דין
ממון לא בעינן, din mamon lo ba'inan, you don't need that aspect
of it being considered your property. ומר סבר, u'mar savar, the other
one holds, דין ממון נמי בעינן. din mamon nami ba'inan. No, you
also need, it's not enough to be able to eat it, you
also need to be able to be considered your property. So מאי
בינייהו? mai beinayhu? So what's a case that would be a difference?
A case that would be able to be eaten, we need now,
but that you are not considered to be really be the technically
the monetary owner of it. That would be the difference. Is it
enough to have היתר אכילה? heter akhila? Everybody agrees that's necessary. Is
that sufficient? Or do you also need דין ממון? din mamon? So
what's the difference? איכא בינייהו מעשר שני שבירושלים. ika beinayhu ma'aser sheni
she'b'Yerushalayim. So I already told you this. מעשר שני ma'aser sheni in
ירושלים Yerushalayim where there's a מצווה mitzvah to eat, so of course
there's a היתר אכילה. heter akhila. But maybe it's not considered yours.
ואליבא דרבי מאיר, v'aliba d'Rabbi Meir, according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
who says that it's considered ממון גבוה, mamon gavoha, it's God's property
that you're eating in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, not yours. Okay. All right. So
that was and again, because God's property doesn't mean somebody could come
and steal it out of my house. You know, I still have
the rights and control over it, but technically it is not mine,
it's like כהנים kohanim eating the קרבנות. korbanos. So למאן דאמר, l'man
d'amar, now again, למאן דאמר לפי שאין בו היתר אכילה, l'man d'amar
lefi she'ein bo heter akhila, if the only concern was you're able
to eat it, הרי יש בה היתר אכילה, harey yesh ba heter
akhila, you're able to eat it and you'd be יוצא. yotze. ולמאן
דאמר לפי שאין בו דין ממון, u'l'man d'amar lefi she'ein bo din
mamon, if the issue is that in addition to being able to
eat it, you have to be the owner of it, מעשר שני
ממון גבוה הוא, ma'aser sheni mamon gavoha hu, you would not be
considered the owner and therefore according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir at
least you would not be יוצא. yotze. Now our משנה, mishna, you
might remember, says you're יוצא yotze with מעשר שני ma'aser sheni in
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. But fine, so that would be those that are not
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and say that מעשר שני ma'aser sheni in
ירושלים Yerushalayim is considered your money. So our משנה mishna isn't going
to be a problem because there always is someone who says that
מעשר שני ma'aser sheni in ירושלים Yerushalayim is your property. But according
to this the argument would be at least according to רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir you would not be יוצא yotze if you need not
only the ability to eat it but also for it to be
able to be considered your money. And let's just see how the
גמרא Gemara now sort of concludes this point about who holds what.
תסתיים, tistayem, let us let us conclude, דרבי אסי דאמר לפי שאין
בו דין ממון, d'Rabbi Assi d'amar lefi she'ein bo din mamon, because
we said it was a debate of רבי אסי Rabbi Assi and
רבי חייא בר אבין, Rabbi Hiyya bar Abbin, but we didn't know
who said what. Let's prove that רבי אסי Rabbi Assi is the
one that requires the דין ממון, din mamon, also the aspect of
ownership. How should you prove that? דאמר רבי אסי, d'amar Rabbi Assi,
because רבי אסי Rabbi Assi says, אתרוג של מעשר שני לדברי רבי
מאיר אין אדם יוצא בו ידי חובתו ביום טוב, esrog shel ma'aser
sheni l'divrei Rabbi Meir ein adam yotze bo yedei hovato b'yom tov,
because he says exactly what we said, that he says that according
to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir you're not יוצא yotze with מעשר שני
ma'aser sheni in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. ולדברי חכמים אדם יוצא בו ידי חובתו
ביום טוב, u'l'divrei hakhamim adam yotze bo yedei hovato b'yom tov, but
according to the חכמים, hakhamim, which would be our משנה, mishna, you
would, because they say מעשר שני ma'aser sheni in ירושלים Yerushalayim is
your money. But רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who says it's God's money
would say you're not יוצא. yotze. תסתיים, tistayem, that's a good proof.
You see according to רבי אסי Rabbi Assi it is not enough
to have the permission to ability to eat it, you also need
to be considered the monetary owner and therefore the one case that
would be the difference would be מעשר שני ma'aser sheni in ירושלים
Yerushalayim according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Yes, Dov? Just I I'm
not holding on to the requirement of לכם. lakhem. anybody argue against
you don't need to own it if the פסוק passuk says clearly
לכם? lachem? No, that's a good point, that's why I was trying
to say before, not the issue of ownership per se, but the
issue—and the גמרא Gemara doesn't say ownership, it says דין ממון. din
mammon. So one aspect of דין ממון din mammon is a question
of like of technically is it considered to have value. Okay? So
for example something that's אסור בהנאה, assur behana'ah, it might—so there is
a debate in the פוסקים poskim whether I'm considered the owner or
not, let's say. But it doesn't have value. Just because it doesn't
have value doesn't mean that you can come and take it out
of my house, right? If I have this ערלה orlah אסור בהנאה,
assur behana'ah, right? So it's like a technical issue of to what
degree am I considered to be the full owner even though practically
I do have control. מעשר שני בירושלים, Maaser Sheni biYerushalayim, it's true
it's considered like God's money and not my money. On the other
hand, if I come with my 2,000 crates of oranges into ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, you can't say, oh well we פוסקן pasken like ר' מאיר
Rabbi Meir and then grab my crates of oranges away from me
because it's not yours. Okay? Technically I'm the one who has—you know—I'm
still the one who has control, I'm still the one who has
the מצוה mitzvah to eat it. It's just that you know in
a somehow in a technical sense it's like considered God's and not
mine. But again in a practical sense I'm still the owner. So
that's—but it is a good point, we are—nobody is saying like, oh
you could use somebody else's, right? It's—you know what would be an
interesting question? Right? If you go ahead and say to me, you
know Rabbi Winzer, I'm allowing you to eat my אתרוג, etrog, okay?
Like you know when I say here you can have an apple,
I welcome you to my house and I say here have an
apple, right? I've given you this example before. Can you say, okay
thank you, and take the apple and leave? You know, maybe. But
probably what I'm doing is I'm not giving you the apple as
a gift, right? I'm probably giving you the right to eat my
apple. Okay? So let's say you said to me here you can
eat my אתרוג. etrog. I say, oh okay so I have a
היתר אכילה hetter achilah now I can use it on the first
day יום טוב? Yom Tov? No, because you're still the owner there,
right? So here we're dealing with a case where nobody else has
competing ownership, I'm the only one that has the owner, but nevertheless
there's a technical issue about whether it's considered to be, you know,
fully—in a technical sense am I fully considered to be the owner?
Like you're the renter. Well, I don't know if I would say
that. But the point by all of these is nobody is denying
that you—let's put it this way, nobody else can be the owner.
That's certainly true. Okay? And you start fundamentally as the owner, but
in some technical way there's a lack of you being considered like
somehow fully the owner. It's not fully considered to be an object
of value or it's considered somehow God's ממון. mammon. But again it
is a good point that nobody is denying the need for לכם.
lachem. The other interesting thing to underscore since you bring up the
לכם lachem point is is that therefore all of this would only
be an issue on יום טוב ראשון Yom Tov Rishon if it's
all rooted in the לכם lachem idea. And again that's why רמב"ם
Rambam says the issue about being able to eat it is a
seven-day issue because it's about being defined as a fruit. But if
all of these ownership and the דין ממון, din mammon, the technical
value aspect and the ability to eat are aspects of defining ownership,
then all of this is only a problem on the first day.
Okay, so let's now continue. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
גופא. Gufa. אמר רבי אסי: Amar Rabbi Assi: אתרוג של מעשר שני—now
Etrog shel Maaser Sheni we're going to look at this issue assuming
that there is this דין din of דין ממון. din mammon. אתרוג
של מעשר שני לדברי רבי מאיר אין אדם יוצא בו ידי חובתו
בפסח, Etrog shel Maaser Sheni ledirei Rabbi Meir ein adam yotzei bo
yedei chovato bePesach, לדברי חכמים אדם יוצא בו ידי חובתו בפסח. ledirei
Chachamim adam yotzei bo yedei chovato bePesach. Okay, so that we've already
been discussing because whether it's considered yours or God's property. עיסה של
מעשר שני—let's Issa shel Maaser Sheni say you have dough that you
made out of מעשר שני Maaser Sheni flour in ירושלים—לדברי רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir פטור מן החלה, according to ר' מאיר Rabbi Meir you
don't have to take חלה, challah, it's not your dough. לדברי חכמים
חייב בחלה. ledirei Chachamim chayav bachallah. I'm sorry did I skip a
line? I skipped a line. Yeah, okay, I'm sorry. So אתרוג של
מעשר שני לדברי רבי מאיר אין אדם יוצא בו ידי חובתו ביום
טוב לדברי חכמים אדם יוצא בו ידי חובתו ביום טוב. etrog shel
Maaser Sheni ledirei Rabbi Meir ein adam yotzei bo yedei chovato beYom
Tov ledirei Chachamim adam yotzei bo yedei chovato beYom Tov. מצה של
מעשר שני—let's matzah shel Maaser Sheni say you make מצה matzah out
of מעשר שני Maaser Sheni flour and you're in ירושלים—לדברי רבי מאיר
Rebbi Meir אין אדם יוצא בו ידי חובתו בפסח ein adam yotzei
bo yedei chovato bePesach because it's—אין אדם יוצא yotzei בו ידי חובתו
בפסח because you don't—because it's not yours. לדברי חכמים אדם יוצא בו
ידי חובתו בפסח ledirei Chachamim adam yotzei bo yedei chovato bePesach according
to חכמים Chachamim you are because it is yours. עיסה של מעשר
שני Issa shel Maaser Sheni if you have dough made out of
מעשר שני, Maaser Sheni, לדברי רבי מאיר פטור מן החלה ledirei Rabbi
Meir patur min hachallah, according to ר' מאיר Rabbi Meir it's exempt
because it's not yours, לדברי חכמים חייב בחלה. ledirei Chachamim chayav bachallah.
Okay. מתקיף לה רב פפא, Matkif leh Rav Pappa, רב פפא Rav
Pappa asks this: בשלמא עיסה, Bishlama issa, I get why the dough
is also an aspect of ownership, כתיב ראשית עריסותיכם, k'tiv reshith arisoteichem,
the first of yours, possessive, your kneading troughs. אתרוג נמי כתיב לכם,
Etrog nami k'tiv lachem, by אתרוג etrog it says yours, ולקחתם לכם,
u'lekachtem lachem, obviously you need ownership. So this idea that it's considered
God's, again even though you have control over it and you eat
it, that could be an exclusion according to ר' מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
Right. משלכם mishlachem it has to be yours. אלא מצה מי כתיב
מצתכם? Ella matzah mi k'tiv matzatchem? It doesn't say your מצה, matzah,
there's no possessive by מצה. matzah. So אמר רבה בר שמואל ואיתימא
רב ירמיה בר שמואל. Amar Rabba bar Shmuel v'itayma Rav Yirmiyah bar
Shmuel. שמיא shmaya אתיא atya לחם לחם. lechem lechem. Oh, it's a
גזרה שוה gzeirah shava of bread bread. כתיב הכא ksiv hacha לחם
עוני, lechem oni, poor person's bread, וכתיב התם, u'chsiv hatam, it says
over there, והיה באכלכם מלחם הארץ, vihaya be'acholchem milechem ha'aretz, by by
by חלה. challah. So the same way מה להלן משלכם, mah lahalan
mishlachem, the same way the bread of the חלה challah has to
be yours, ולא משום מעשר, ve'lo mishum ma'aser, אף כאן משלכם ולא
משום מעשר. af kan mishlachem ve'lo mishum ma'aser. Here too it is
the same, yours and not מעשר. ma'aser. So the גמרא Gemara says,
לימא מסייע ליה, leima misayia leh, let's try to bring a proof
to this. עיסה, Issa, by the way, just want to stop for
a moment and notice the somewhat significant the possible significance of the
difference of לכם lachem by by סוכות Sukkot and not by by
פסח. Pesach. At סוכות Sukkot we also had חג הסכות תעשה לך,
chag haSukkot ta'aseh lecha, right, לך lecha למיעוטי גזולה, limutei gzeulah, לכם
lachem is למיעוטי גזולה, limutei gzeulah, and the whole idea by the
way of סוכה, Sukkah, right remember רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer, you have
to dwell in it, you know, for for the whole seven days,
14 meals, you can't use somebody else's סוכה, Sukkah, even the חכמים
chachamim that disagree, the idea of סוכות Sukkot is much more this
idea of ownership and rootedness. Your house, right according to the רשב"ם
Rashbam the whole reason you take the ארבעה מינים arba minim is
cause you're going to grow and it's going to be the time
you gather in all of your fruit from the field, ואספתם, ve'asaftem,
you gather in everything and you want to rejoice and say thanks
to God so you take these ארבעה מינים arba minim to thank
God for all of your prosperity. So סוכות Sukkot very much has
this idea of your rootedness in the land, your ownership, your house
and then sort of recognizing God and thanking God within that context
whereas פסח Pesach is all about leaving מצרים Mitzrayim and going out
into the wilderness, right, and it's all about this sort of non-ownership
state and sort of recognizing almost the sort of collective rather than
the individual. So it is actually interesting to think about the fact
that the לך lecha comes twice by סוכות, Sukkot, right, חג הסכות
תעשה לך, chag haSukkot ta'aseh lecha, ולקחתם לכם, u'lekachtem lachem, and the
גמרא Gemara here says פשט, pshat, it doesn't say מצתכם matzotchem anywhere.
There's no concept of this ownership doesn't get underscored anywhere by פסח.
Pesach. This is according to הלכה? halacha? Not clear. This is according
to this according to who it is, to רבי אסי. Rebbi Assi.
Okay, not clear if we actually rule that way. Alright, but this
is רבי אסי's Rebbi Assi now tries to demand a לכם lachem
aspect by מצה. matzah. It's worth noting that it did not start
that way. Yes. It's interesting the contrast because the סוכות Sukkot are
related to פסח Pesach in what way? The idea of סוכה? Sukkah?
Oh because בסכות הושבתי basukkot hoshavti בהוציאי אותם מארץ מצרים. behotzi'i otam
me'eretz mitzrayim. Right. So there are those obviously different elements but clearly
there's also an element of a סוכה Sukkah which is you know,
you know, this is the point that the רשב"ם Rashbam underscored, you
know your your prosperity, your you know your sense of being secure
in your home in the land and you go out of your
home into the סוכה Sukkah to recognize God's hand. So there is
that issue about פסח Pesach is you know, a lot of סוכות
Sukkot situates you after you've come into the land and settled in
the land whereas פסח Pesach is very much situating you at the
moment of leaving מצרים. Mitzrayim. Okay, so but we're making a גזרה
שוה. gzeirah shava. לימא מסייע ליה, leima misayia leh, let's try to
bring a proof. We have a ברייתא braita that says the following:
עיסה של מעשר שני פטורה מן החלה, issa she'ma'aser sheni ptura min
hachallah, דברי מאיר divrei Meir וחכמים אומרים חייבת בחלה. vechachamim omrim chayaves
bachallah. There's the debate by the by the issue about the dough
and חלה, challah, exactly this debate of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and
the חכמים. chachamim. גמרא Gemara says לימא מסייע ליה, leima misayia leh,
maybe I'll bring a proof, hee hee that's exactly what we said,
that maybe it's a proof. So גמרא Gemara says no, אלא מדבהא
פליגי בהא נמי פליגי. ella mi de'vaha pligi baha nami pligi. Clearly
they debate the issue of חלה. challah. The question is do they
also debate the issue of אתרוג etrog and of מצה? matzah? Okay.
או דלמא שאני עיסה, o dilma shani issa, maybe the dough case
is different, אמר קרא עריסותיכם עריסותיכם תרי זימני. amar kra arisoteichem arisoteichem
tray zimnei. Twice it says in the verse your kneading troughs. So
there there's an idea of full ownership. But maybe number one as
we already pointed out מצה, matzah, maybe we don't need it at
all, it never says מצתכם. matzotchem. That's the most tenuous. And even
by אתרוג etrog we saw it was debated whether there's this issue
of דין ממון din mamon in addition to היתר אכילה. heter achilah.
And maybe because maybe just because it says לכם, lachem, so it's
enough לכם lachem you're able to eat it, you have control over
it, that technically it matters that it's considered ממון גבוה mamon gavoha
maybe that's only a problem by חלה challah not by these things.
And that's exactly what we're debating. So again, to answering your point,
obviously everybody agrees you need לכם lachem by אתרוג, etrog, but that
we should interpret לכם lachem so much that even if in practice
you eat it, you control it, you know, you know nobody else
is allowed to get it, is it also a problem that technically
according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir. it's ממון גבוה? mamon gavoha? That's
not so clear. That's the issue here. And can I read this
together because the גמרא Gemara ends on this note, clearly it's telling
me that להלכה la'halacha it's not applicable by מצה? matzah? No. No,
I mean the גמרא, Gemara, you know you can take again, yeah,
but the גמרא Gemara as as I've often said, the גמרא Gemara
is is only very very tangentially interested in in discussing what the
הלכה halacha is. So you know that's left to the ראשונים Rishonim
to try to figure it out and infer it. And that's why
there's often a lot of debate. Okay, so תרומה טמאה פסולה. truma
tme'ah psula. Now that we've established that there are these two criteria
everyone agrees you have to be able to eat it and maybe
also a technical issue of you know of. even in the fullest
technical way being the owner, we're going to go through the משנה
mishnah and identify what the problems are. Obviously most of the problems
in the משנה mishnah you achieve are in the category that you
can't eat it. So תרומה טמאה פסולה truma t'mea psula ולית בה
היתר אכילה v'leit bei heter achila you can't eat תרומה טמאה. truma
t'mea. But תרומה טהורה לא יטול truma t'hora lo yitol don't take
תרומה טהורה truma t'hora now that we have to figure out. So
why not לכתחילה? l'chat-chila? בדיעבד bedi'eved you're יוצא yotzei because you can
eat תרומה טהורה. truma t'hora. Now by the way even if you're
not a כהן kohen you're יוצא yotze because it is edible by
a Jew a כהן kohen can eat it. Which by the way
works out very nicely according to the רמב"ם Rambam because if the
idea of being edible makes the definition of me being the owner
why do I care that a כהן kohen can eat it? I
can't eat it. So if the idea of being able to eat
it defines my ownership relationship where does that happen by תרומה טהורה?
truma t'hora? But if the idea is that it has to be
edible to be considered a fruit then it's fine as long as
somebody's able to eat it. So תוספות Tosafos in order to answer
that question says yes but I could still give it to my
friend the כהן kohen to eat it and therefore since I can
still control who eats it or give it to a grandson who's
a כהן kohen even if I'm not a כהן kohen maybe my
daughter married a כהן kohen that therefore is enough to be considered
the owner that I'm still in control of that. Okay but again
it's a little bit interesting that I don't have to be the
one to be able to eat it. So but let's figure out
why לכתחילה l'chat-chila you're not supposed to take it. So פליגי בר
אמי ורב אסי pligi bar Ami v'rav Assi it's a debate of
בר אמי bar Ami and רב אסי. rav Assi. חד אמר משום
דמכשרא chad amar mishum d'machshira because when you take the אתרוג esrog
and you take it together with the לולב lulav and the לולב
lulav you've been putting in water to keep it fresh so there's
water dripping on the לולב lulav and we find that out in
a later משנה mishnah that they would put the לולב lulav in
water so then it's going to make the אתרוג esrog susceptible to
becoming טמא. tamei. Right when a fruit is picked and it comes
in contact with water after it's picked or any food comes in
contact with water after it's been defined as a fruit that's when
it becomes susceptible for טומאה. tuma. So you want to protect the
תרומה truma from becoming טמא tamei but the best way to protect
it right? The best way to keep your diet is not to
buy the ice cream in the first place not to put it
in the freezer and try not to eat it. So the best
way to protect it is preventing it from being susceptible for טומאה.
tuma. So that's why you shouldn't take it because you'll get it
in contact with water. All right so וחד אמר v'chad amar the
other one says משום דמפסדא mishum d'mafsida no the fact that you're
taking it every day of סוכות Succos and you're handling it means
you're rubbing away at the rind and you're causing some waste to
something that is תרומה. truma. So מאי בינייהו mai beinaihu what would
be a difference? So the easiest difference is that the אתרוג esrog
already had become susceptible had already been in contact with water but
the גמרא's Gemara going to give a more complicated way of sort
of test case מאי בינייהו mai beinaihu what would be a difference?
כגון דקרא ליה שם חוץ מקליפתה החיצונית k'gon dekara lei shem chutz
miklipasa hachitzonis you took this אתרוג esrog how did you make it
תרומה? truma? Because you had a whole box of אתרוגים esrogim and
this אתרוג esrog you took and you said I'm making this אתרוג
esrog תרומה truma but you know which part I'm making תרומה? truma?
Only the meat on the inside not the rind. The rind isn't
תרומה truma only the inside of it is תרומה. truma. You can
do that okay? Because you get to define which part of all
of your stuff is תרומה. truma. So therefore if you wear away
the rind you're not wasting any תרומה truma because only the meat
middle is תרומה. truma. I understand it's like a פסיק רישא psik
reisha in other words I can't pick up the rind only without
also using the תרומה truma that's on the inside. So what? But
meaning when you first made it תרומה truma you said only the
middle not the rind it means when I come to give it
to the כהן kohen I'll say to the כהן kohen here's your
תרומה truma remember to give me back the rind the rind is
still mine I only made תרומה truma the middle part of it.
So now you have an אתרוג esrog that the middle part is
תרומה truma the outer part is not so there's no concern of
wearing away the outer part because the outer part isn't תרומה. truma.
And there's no איסור issur in using תרומה? truma? No as long
as you're not מפסד mafsid it okay? So כגון דקרא ליה שם
חוץ מקליפתה החיצונית k'gon dekara lei shem chutz miklipasa hachitzonis למאן דאמר
משום דמכשרא l'man d'amar mishum d'machshira if the concern is you're making
it susceptible for being טמא tamei איכא ika that's still a problem
because it's still coming in contact with water and then if the
outer rind becomes טמא tamei you don't say oh the outer rind
became טמא. tamei. If טומאה tuma touches water touches the outer part
of it it's all susceptible טומאה tuma touches the outer part of
it it's all טמא. tamei. So איכא ika it's still a problem.
מאן דאמר משום דמפסדא man d'amar mishum d'mafsida if the issue is
wasting it ליכא leika it's not a problem because the rind is
not תרומה. truma. Okay ואם נטל כשרה v'im natal keshera if you
took it it's כשר. kasher. למאן דאמר מפני שאין בה היתר אכילה
l'man d'amar mipnei she'ein bah heter achila if the concern is there's
no היתר אכילה heter achila הרי יש בה היתר אכילה harei yesh
bah heter achila you're able to eat it. Again even if you're
not able to eat it somebody is able to eat it so
according to the רמבּ"ם Rambam that makes it fruit and according to
the other approach of ownership the fact that you can give it
to someone to eat is enough to make it defined as you
own it. למאן דאמר מפני שאין בה דין ממון l'man d'amar mipnei
she'ein bah din mamon and if the issue is not only eating
but as we said before but also technical issue of monetary you
know of a full monetary ownership הרי יש בה דין ממון harei
yesh bah din mamon so you're a full monetary owner of the
תרומה truma and it is not a problem. Of course an interesting
question would be what if you took תרומה truma before you gave
it to the כהן? kohen? Right? There you are considered to be
not really the owner of the תרומה truma you have the right
to decide who gets it but but he's the full owner. But
then there's a scenario where I took the תרומה terumah from my
all of my אתרוגים, esrogim, this I took, and I haven't yet
given it to a כהן. kohen. So there I'm not the owner,
but I do own it enough to decide who gets it. Would
that be considered enough for the דין ממון? din mamon? That is
not being explored by the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, so that is an
interesting question. That I think it would be very questionable whether or
not you would be considered to be enough of the לכם, lachem,
of the owner. That's just not a technical problem, there you really
aren't the owner. You have a right to give it to somebody,
but you really aren't the owner. That could be a real issue.
Okay, moving on. ושל דמאי. veshel demai. דמאי demai is a debate
of בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. בית הלל
Beit Hillel says you're יוצא yotze? בדיעבד. bediavad. Okay, so מאי טעמא
דבית הלל? mai ta'ama de-Beit Hillel? What's בית הלל's Beit Hillel's reasoning
that בדיעבד bediavad you're יוצא? yotze לכתחילה lichatchila not, because it's sort
of like טבל, tevel, and the same way you're not יוצא yotze
with טבל tevel because you can't eat, you're not יוצא yotze. with
דמאי. demai. But why בדיעבד bediavad yes? So כיון דאי בעי מפקר
להו לנכסיה והוי עני וחזי ליה, kivan de-i ba'ei mafkir lehu lenichsei
vehavei ani vachazi lei, you could renounce ownership of your property and
become a poor person, and then you'd be allowed to eat דמאי,
demai, because the poor people are allowed to eat the דמאי. demai.
It's a Rabbinic requirement and the Rabbis waived the requirement for the
poor. So הכא נמי לכם קרינא ביה, hacha nami lachem karena bei,
therefore here it's still considered to be yours. Now by the way,
as תוספות Tosafot points out, you really don't need that reason, because
it's like תרומה. terumah. As long as there's somebody that can eat
the דמאי, demai, I could give it to a poor person, even
if I can't, that should be enough to be considered היתר אכילה.
heter achila. And I certainly own it, right? Because I just take
תרומות ומעשרות terumot uma'asrot and then I can eat the rest. So
תוספות Tosafot says actually it's the גמרא Gemara is sort of making
an overstatement. You don't really need to say I could be able
to eat it. It could be that somebody can eat it like
the תרומה, terumah, and that's enough, and I certainly am the owner
of it, and therefore that's enough. דתנן, detnan, we taught in the
משנה, mishnah, מאכילין את העניים דמאי ואת האכסניא דמאי. machilin et ha-aniyim
demai ve'et ha-achsenia demai. You can feed the עניים aniyim דמאי demai
and the אכסניא. achsenia. אכסניא achsenia often means like a guest, but
here it's explained to be sort of like troops that you're quartering.
So you're allowed to give them this stuff, and you're not like
you're feeding them איסור. issur. Now that's why you're allowed to give
them. How are they allowed to eat it? So obviously the inference
is that an עני ani is allowed to eat דמאי. demai. ובית
שמאי, u-Beit Shammai, so what would בית שמאי's Beit Shammai's response be?
עני לא אכיל דמאי, ani lo achil demai, an עני ani isn't
allowed to eat דמאי demai according to בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. דתנן,
detnan, we taught in the משנה, mishnah, מאכילין את העניים דמאי machilin
et ha-aniyim demai ואת האכסניא דמאי. ve'et ha-achsenia demai. So you can
feed the poor people דמאי demai and the quartered troops דמאי. demai.
ואמר רב הונא תניא, ve-amar Rav Huna tanyia, we taught in a
ברייתא, braita, בית שמאי אומרים אין מאכילין את העניים ואת האכסניא דמאי.
Beit Shammai omrim ein machilin et ha-aniyim ve'et ha-achsenia demai. בית הלל
אומרים מאכילין את העניים דמאי ואת האכסניא דמאי. Beit Hillel omrim machilin
et ha-aniyim demai ve'et ha-achsenia demai. It's a debate of בית הלל
Beit Hillel and בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. So therefore that's בית שמאי's
Beit Shammai's reason. He says that דמאי demai is not edible in
its current state and therefore it does not have a היתר אכילה.
heter achila. Is it that it becomes מותר muttar or it's a
type of like פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh or שעת הדחק sha'at hadechak
type of... No, the understanding is... Well, soldiers is an interesting question,
Jewish soldiers or not Jewish soldiers. If it's not Jewish soldiers, what's
the חידוש? chiddush? The חידוש chiddush might just be that it's not
considered like for you like a הנאת איסור hana'at issur that you
are getting benefit from feeding them and so on. But by the
עניים, aniyim, it says even if they're Jewish, and therefore you have
to say that חז"ל Chazal do not require. One way, conceptual way
of explaining this is, is that דמאי demai is an obligation to
be מפריש דמאי, mafrish demai, but it's not like they turned דמאי
demai into מאכלות אסורות. ma'achalot assurot. Right? So we never feel like,
oh, well, since let's say chicken and milk is only דרבנן, derabbanan,
so poor people can eat chicken and milk if I have some
of that around, right? So it's specifically an issue here, which is
seen as דמאי demai is something inherent to it, it's Rabbinic but
it's also Rabbinic with certain weakness to it, like an understanding that
it might actually already be okay. So therefore it's understood like you
have an obligation to be מפריש, mafrish, but it's not so much
that it's, as we would say in לומדות lamdus language, the חפצא
cheftza of מאכלות אסורות, ma'achalot assurot, and therefore they waived the requirement
by the poor, yes. But there's also פוסקים poskim that you can
feed them דמאי demai but they have to tithe it. No, then
there's no חידוש. chiddush. Yeah, then there's no חידוש. chiddush. Okay, that's
not what we're talking about. Now ומעשר שני בירושלים. uma'aser sheni bi-Yerushalayim.
מעשר שני בירושלים, ma'aser sheni bi-Yerushalayim, the משנה mishnah goes on, you
are יוצא. yotze, So this we've already looked at. למאן דאמר ממונא
גבוה הוא לא קא מכשיר. leman de-amar mamona gavoha hu lo ka
machshir. Oh, but first why are you not allowed to do it
לכתחילה? lichatchila? So you don't do it לכתחילה lichatchila because you might
again, if there's a concern of getting it susceptible for טומאה, tumah,
that's a concern here as well. Same way you can't get your
תרומה terumah טמאה, teme'ah, you're not allowed to get your מעשר שני
ma'aser sheni טמא. tamei. Okay. למאן דאמר משום מפסדא, leman de-amar mishum
mafsada, if the concern is that you waste it because it's no
longer the rind and whatever and stuff you otherwise would have used...
you would have used in another way now gets destroyed. So הרי
מפסדא, harei mafsada, same problem here. So whatever the לכתחילה lichatchila is
by תרומה. terumah. The same types of לכתחילה lechatchila problems exist by
the מעשר שני. Maaser Sheni. If נטל כשרה, natal k'shira, but if
you did take it you're יוצא, yotze so that as well as
we've said. למאן דאמר משום שאין בה היתר אכילה דברי הכל, Leman
de-amar mishum she-ein ba hetter achila divrei hakol, so if the concern
is that you need to be able to eat it, so everybody
would explain why that if that's the only issue, being able to
eat it, so then of course you're יוצא yotze, even according to
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir with מעשר שני Maaser Sheni because all you
need is the ability to be able to eat it. למאן דאמר
לפי שאין בה דין ממון, Leman de-amar lefi she-ein ba din mamon,
the one that says it's not enough to be able to eat
it, you also need to have a full technical ownership over it.
הא מני רבנן היא, ha mani rabanan hi, it's the rabbis that
argue in רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would say
you're not יוצא, yotze, it's God's property, but according to חכמים chachamim
you are יוצא, yotze חכמים chachamim say it's your property. So everybody
would explain that to agree to the משנה Mishnah that you're יוצא
מעשר שני Maaser Sheni in ירושלים Yerushalayim because there's certainly at least
the rabbis who say that it's your property. The only question is
according to רבי מאיר, would רבי מאיר agree? And that's the issue,
whether you need to have full technical monetary ownership or is it
sufficient that you're able to eat it. So that was a whole
sort of self-contained סוגיא sugya where we worked through those two categories
of דין ממון din mamon and היתר אכילה. hetter achila. And now
we shift our attention to the second part of the משנה Mishnah
which is really, I mean, the משנה Mishnah is really different sections.
There's the first the traditional opening גזול יבש gazul yavesh etc. עיר
הנדחת אשרה. ir hanidachat ashera. Then there's this new section about because
it's a fruit talking about whether you're able to eat it or
not and now we move to the final section which is particular
aesthetic aspects. Okay, so let's take a look. עלתה חזזית. alta chazazit.
So if a wart went on the majority over it, it's not
good, on a minority it's okay. And this next גמרא Gemara is
going to sound familiar to a type of גמרא Gemara we had
before by the berries of the הדס. Hadas. אמר רב חסדא. Amar
Rav Chisda. רב חסדא Rav Chisda says דבר זה רבינו הגדול אמרו,
davar ze rabbeinu hagadol amro, our great rabbi said it, which רש״י
Rashi says is רב. Rav. המקום יהיה בעזרו, Hamakom yihiye b'ezro, God
should be by his side. לא שנו אלא במקום אחד. Lo shanu
ela b'makom echad. When is the problem of the wart a majority
of the אתרוג? etrog? If it's all collected in one place. אבל
בשנים ושלשה מקומות Aval b'shnayim u'shlosha mekomot if it's spread over two
or three places even though they covers the majority כשר kasher that's
okay. אמר ליה רבא, Amar lei Rava, so רבא Rava said אדרבה,
aderaba, the opposite makes sense. בשנים ושלשה מקומות הוי ליה כמנומר פסול,
B'shnayim u'shlosha mekomot havlei kemanumar pasul, it's more of a problem if
it's spread over two or three places. It looks spotted. It looks
bigger like it's all over it and it should be invalid. אלא
אי איתמר אסיפא איתמר. Ela i itmar aseifa itmar. Fine, you're right.
This issue of centralized or spread out was not said at the
first case, which was the case about the majority, that's a problem
regardless. It was said on the second part of the משנה Mishnah
when it's a minority it's כשר. kasher. על מיעוטו כשר, Al miuto
kasher, the end of the משנה Mishnah says if this wart is
on a minority it's kosher. אמר רב חסדא. Amar Rav Chisda. דבר
זה רבינו הגדול אמרו והמקום יהיה בעזרו. Davar ze rabbeinu hagadol amro
ve-Hamakom yihiye b'ezro. רב Rav said this and God should be by
his side. לא שנו אלא במקום אחד. Lo shanu ela b'makom echad.
When is it okay that if it's on a minority of the
אתרוג etrog that it's כשר? kasher? That's if it is in one
location. אבל בשנים ושלשה מקומות הוי ליה כמנומר ופסול, Aval b'shnayim u'shlosha
mekomot havlei kemanumar u-pasul, in two or three places it's spotted and
invalid. So that then becomes now what started off as a leniency
becomes a big חומרא. chumra. Any two or three warts, now this
isn't spot, חזזית chazazit is like a wart. Have people ever seen
אתרוגים etrogim with these like you know unusual growths like they're essentially
you know, so anyways those types of warts in two or three
places, a two really becomes two or three, but two is already
invalid. דאמר רבא, De-amar Rava, and רבא Rava also says ועל חוטמו,
ve-al chotmo, if it's on the חוטם, chotam, the nose, literally meaning
the upper incline of the אתרוג. etrog. רש״י Rashi basically says it's
where you know the אתרוג etrog sort of has like a thick
central body and then it starts sloping, so רש״י Rashi says the
חוטמת chotemet is the part where it begins to slope upwards, okay,
literally the nose. ואפילו במשהו נמי פסול, Ve-afilu b'mashehu nami pasul, even
a little bit is invalid and this then becomes an issue because
it's very visible and this then becomes the issue of a little
bit of how little, like you know you know people they're very
מאוד מקפיד me'od makpid even a tiniest little black dot, certainly if
it's directly under the פיטם, pitam, but really anywhere to the top
third they say they look for tiny little, so that's based on
this hypersensitivity at the place of the חוטמו, chotmo, the upward slope.
Although the גמרא Gemara is talking about a חזזית chazazit and most
people get worried or you know if you're worried you tend to
be worried even about a little black dot, okay, but that is
but that's certainly where some of that concern comes from. Let's read
one more line, no, do we have one more minute? We have
one minute. ניטל פטמתו, Nital pitmato, if the פיטמתא pitamta is removed,
the פיטם. pitam. תני רב יצחק בן אלעזר Tani Rav Yitzchak ben
Elazar ניטל בוכנתו. nital bochanto. To make it clear what the פיטם
pitam is, he describes it as the בוכנא. bochna. Now the בוכנא
bochna is a pestle. But is that what what's the one that
you bang, the mortar or the pestle? Pestle. The pestle. So if
so if the pestle, if you see look what a pestle looks
like, right, a pestle looks like sort of like this and like
this, right? Because you hold it and then it's got this bulbous
top to bang with. So that's actually what a פיטם pitam looks
like. So he's describing the פיטם pitam you should know which end,
I mean flip it, right, is is the is the is the...
Now I will say that there are some ראשונים *rishonim* that actually
actually identify the פטום *pitom* as the opposite end, as the as
the what do you call it the stem, the stem. So what's
the difference between that and the statement in the גמרא *Gemara* where
it says if the עוקץ *oketz* is removed it's okay? Because what
they say is if you think about how something exists in a
in a thing, it's got like a part that sort of goes
in, right? And then it's right and then it's got like, you
know, it's got like this twig that comes out, right? But you
know, but it's got a part that sort of like in right
it's sort of like a sort of star thing like you know
what I mean? So anyway so they say the עוקץ *oketz* is
the part that's external. The פטום *pitom* they'll say is the part
that's sort of inside of the fruit and that this is the
פטום *pitom* and that that's what it means when you remove the
פטום *pitom* it's invalid. We obviously do not פוסקן *pasken* that way.
We פוסקן *pasken* the פטום *pitom* is the other end and, you
know, that obviously makes the most sense in terms of this idea
of thinking about it as a pestle. I'll just end by pointing
your bringing your attention to one interesting רש״י *Rashi* by the way,
when the גמרא *Gemara* says that תרומה *Terumah* was היתר אכילה *hetter
achila*, right? And I said because a כהן *kohen* can eat it.
If you look at the רש״י *Rashi*, he says הרי יש בה
היתר אכילה *harei yesh bah hetter achila*, I don't know where to
tell you it is, anyway the end of that רש״י *Rashi* says,
he says אבל פדיון אין לה *aval pidyon ein lah*. So apparently
there was somebody who explained the reason תרומה *Terumah* has a היתר
אכילה *hetter achila* is because you could redeem תרומה *Terumah* and eat
it, which is completely false, right? So only a כהן *kohen* can
eat it. So רש״י *Rashi* says אבל פדיון אין לה להיות ניתרת
לאכילת ישראל והאומר כן רשע הוא *aval pidyon ein lah lehiyot niteret
la'achilat Yisrael veha'omer ken rasha hu*. So I thought that was quite
fascinating. It's not just a wrong interpretation. You're going to be מכשיא
*makhshia* people. You're going to make people think you can eat תרומה
*Terumah* if you redeem it. So apparently there was that interpretation the
גמרא *Gemara* was completely false, but I like that line in רש״י
*Rashi* והאומר כן רשע הוא *ha'omer ken rasha hu*. Okay, we'll end
with that lovely thought for today.